Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Madam.
What's going on, Jade?
You almost knocked into me.
Nothing.
I didn't listen to Consort Fleur on An Bihuai's case.
She's been having a tantrum for a few days.
I have to do something to soothe her.
You know that I treat you differently from anyone else.
I dare not think that way.
It's just that I still dread to think about
what Yu and Concubine Beauté did.
I understand your apprehension.
I had the intention to promote you to Concubine.
But the duration of your service is relatively short,
and you were promoted to Noble Lady as an exception.
I'm afraid you'll have to settle for it at the moment.
You'll have a justifiable promotion when you're pregnant.
Huan Huan cares nothing about her rank.
As long as you have me in your heart, Si Lang.
I always do.
I hold you very dear to my heart.
I could only have peace of mind
here with you in the entire harem.
I understand.
You visited Meizhuang.
Does she have a better appetite now?
She's still the same, craving for sour food.
[Sour food was believed to help with getting a boy.]
When will you have a baby boy of our own?
Why does it have to be a boy?
Why not a girl?
I'll love our child just the same.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Where are you heading to, Lingrong?
I'm going to visit Meizhuang.
How coincidental!
His Majesty is going with me too.
- Let's go together.
- Yes.
Let's go.
Lady Vertu, you look very well.
I believe you'll give birth to a healthy child.
His Majesty the Emperor.
May peace be with Your Majesty.
What a coincidence!
Everyone is here today.
Since Lady Vertu is pregnant, I must provide
the best care for her as the head of the harem.
We follow Her Majesty.
Rise, rise.
Here, sit down.
How are you? How are you feeling today?
I'm very well. I thank Your Majesty.
I wonder if Your Majesty had dinner yet.
I have a new cook in my palace.
He cooks the best Jiangnan cuisine.
I had dinner at Bitong Shuyuan.
[bitong: verdant phoenix tree; shuyuan: reading yard]
I believe Lady Sourire must have
a good cook as well to keep Your Majesty for dinner.
His Majesty always remembers the
ejiao longan soup at Your Highness's palace.
[from the night when Meizhuang almost drowned]
Now that Your Highness has another good cook,
His Majesty would even visit Your Highness in his dreams.
It's been over a month since we last spoke.
Lady Sourire has a way with words just as always.
This young lady has a sharp tongue.
Are you going to wage a war of words with her?
Your Majesty, I always like to banter with
Lady Sourire for her sharpness of wit.
Your Majesty, General of Ili offered tributary cantaloupe.
Please have some with us.
Certainly.
Your Majesty, it's time to select a name tag.
It's all right. I'll visit the Empress.
If you have cantaloupe, I'll eat with you later.
Sure.
Lady Sourire, you can spend more time with Lady Vertu.
Yes.
Who's hiding over there?
- We saw you!
- Come here!
Don't arrest me!
I'm Lady Vertu's maid.
You ... you are the maid Poria?
Why were you sneaking about?
What is it that you are carrying?
What is this?
Huh?
Were you trying to run away with Lady Vertu's belongings?
What a disgraced servant! Take her out and ...
Eh ...
You're pregnant. Don't worry yourself about it.
My Lady ... Help me, My Lady!
How can I tolerate you anymore?
Aiya, get out of my sight!
Hold on.
This ...
(gasp) What is this?
Blood ...
Why ... is there blood on the pants?
Could it be ... a rob-and-murder?
That is strange.
Why would you steal nothing valuable but some filthy clothes?
Are these the belongings of Lady Vertu?
Why are they covered with blood?
Is it because ... Lady Vertu is having her menses?
I'm not ...
Your Majesty, this maid is suspicious.
In my humble opinion, she should be
interrogated by the Department of Penalty.
Look what you've done with your paws.
Take her out!
My Lady...
My Lady,
I was destroying the evidence for you.
But you would ruthlessly send me to death.
Why should I remain loyal to you?
Your Majesty ... Your Majesty ...
I dare not hide the truth from Your Majesty any more.
Lady Vertu is not pregnant at all.
Nor was I stealing the clothes.
Lady Vertu had a menstruation and stained her pants.
She asked me to throw them out.
These are the ironclad proof.
Aiya, Meizhuang ...
Your Majesty ... She is trying to slander me.
Lady Vertu had a shock.
Send for the doctors.
Mr Su,
please send for Dr Liu
who has been attending to my pregnancy.
I wonder if he's on shift tonight.
My Lady, Dr Liu is not on shift tonight.
It's all right.
Send for the infirmary head, Zhang Mi.
Your Majesty, Dr Liu has always been looking after my ...
It doesn't' matter!
All imperial doctors are the same.
Dr Zhang, what is going on?
Was her pregnancy affected?
I beg Your Majesties' forgiveness.
Lady Vertu ...
she shows no symptoms of pregnancy.
Nonsense!
How come I show no symptoms of pregnancy?
Compose yourself, Meizhuang.
It might be a misdiagnosis.
I'm not a specialist in obstetrics.
I'd caution that we consult Dr Jiang Cheng.
Send for him.
Your Majesty, Lady Vertu is not pregnant.
I wonder which doctor diagnosed her pregnancy.
This doesn't make sense.
My Lady has not been menstruating.
She feels nauseous and craves for sour food.
These are all pregnancy symptoms, aren't they?
But in my humble opinion, Lady Vertu
should have menstruated a few days ago.
Her having irregular menstrual cycle
should be the effects of certain medicines.
A few months ago, Lady Vertu asked me
for a prescription to delay her menstruation.
She hoped to adjust her menstrual cycle for a pregnancy.
Although I was hesitant, Lady Vertu said
she was doing it for the imperial family.
So I had to provide the prescription.
As to nausea and her liking for sour food,
I might not be able to know.
Your Majesty, I did ask Dr Jiang for a prescription.
But I was hoping to prepare myself for
pregnancy rather than delay menstruation.
I feel really aggrieved, Your Majesty.
Where's the prescription.
We'll see the proof in black and white.
Lunar,
bring the prescription in the
bottom drawer of my dresser box.
Your Majesty ...
I understand that private receipt of
prescriptions is an offense in the palace.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
Indeed, yet a minor offense
compared to feigning a pregnancy for favor.
My Lady, it was not there!
That is all right.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Bring Liu Ben here immediately.
He'll be roped if he dares to hesitate.
Your Majesty, I sent for Dr Liu as well
when Your Majesty summoned Dr Jiang.
But his residence ... had already been vacated.
Very well then.
Lady Shen, he is from your hometown, isn't he?
And you recommended him to
attend to your pregnancy, didn't you?
Your Majesty ...
Anyone speaking for her will be convicted of the same offence.
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is very close to Lady Vertu.
I wonder if she was ...
Stop it!
May peace be restored in Your Majesty.
You deceived me and the Empress Dowager.
Don't you dare flaunt her hairpin!
[It was considered a disgrace for women
to leave their hair undone in public.]
Your Majesty, your health takes priority.
I always appreciated your stable personality.
I would never expect you to
commit such an unspeakable crime
trying to gain favor with a feigned pregnancy.
I feel extremely disappointed.
Your Majesty, I didn't do it.
I am wrongfully convicted.
Your Majesty, I grew up with Meizhuang
and I can vouch for her character.
If she has made a mistake, I hope Your Majesty will bestow
upon her a chance to redeem herself considering her attentive service.
I beg that Your Highness will reconsider.
I beg of Your Majesty to forgive Lady Shen.
Lady Sourire is not wrong.
Lady Vertu was simply eager to have a child.
I hope Your Majesty will take account of her past service.
The Noble Lady surnamed Shen committed indecent acts.
She is to be demoted to Companion
with deprivation of her honorary name
and confined in the Leisured Moon Chamber
[her residence in the Summer Palace].
No one will be able to visit her without my permission.
Your Majesty, please enlighten us
as for what to do about Liu Ben and Poria.
Capture Liu Ben, alive.
Poria ...
kill.
Meizhuang ...
How could this happen?
How could this happen, Coua?
I'm so scared. Will this affect us?
Don't worry, at least Lady Sourire wasn't affected.
Go quickly ...
this ...
burn this immediately!
Are you sure, My Lady?
You spent a few days working on it.
Anything related to her feigned pregnancy is a taboo for His Majesty.
We would be in dire trouble should it be discovered.
Go, go quickly!
[Liu Ben]
I've done my job. Money.
Of course.
Here's five thousand taels.
It should be enough for half of your life.
Count it before you go.
(sigh) I'm afraid this could only last for six months for me.
What? Liu Ben ran away?
Your Highness please don't worry.
I've sent people in pursuit.
Kill him upon capture.
Liu Ben knows too much about us.
By no means is he to remain.
Yes.
Your Highness.
Rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Is Poria's family taken care of?
Yes, Your Highness.
They have been rewarded amply and sent beyond Rehe Province.
Very well.
I made it clear to Poria that her family would die if she failed.
But I promised her family a lifetime in wealth
even if she had to die to make it successful.
That is very wise, Your Highness.
Poria has died a worthy death for Your Highness and her family.
You may leave.
Here he is.
Mr Zhang!
Peace to Companion An.
Thank you, sir.
Mr Zhang, you agreed yesterday to
bring the packages of My Lady to her family.
Here are the packages.
Thank you for your help, sir!
I'm truly sorry, Miss.
I'm afraid today I cannot deliver a promise I made yesterday.
May I speak to you privately, sir?
Is 20 taels not enough for the trip?
If so, I will collect more for you, sir.
My Lady, over just one night the world has completely changed.
Lady Vertu is now Companion Shen.
I really don't dare to send the packages for you.
Mr Zhang! Mr Zhang!
How can you go back on your word?
At least Lady Sourire is still there.
I'm not going back on my word.
It's just that anything associated with Companion Shen is a taboo.
I should not want anything to do with her.
As for Lady Sourire, she won't remain unscathed
when Companion Shen is down.
In my view, that is "the tail of a rabbit — can't be long".
[He is using a Xie Hou Yu (歇后语), a wait-for-it phrase]
All right, sir, you can tell me frankly
what I can do to have the packages delivered to my mother.
I will keep half of the items.
Be careful. Go quickly.
This one, and that one. Hurry.
Why are you taking away the belongings of my palace?
Companion An, Her Highness said
that you came with Companion Shen.
You do not deserve to live in such an
ornate room according to your rank.
However, by the grace of Her Highness,
you don't have to move to another residence.
It's just that the decorations here ...
are not useful for you, nor are you worthy of them.
Her Highness instructed me to move away all of them.
Since the residences of these servants are not well decorated,
they will be able to keep yours.
(Eunuchs: Let's go.)
Ptui, stop calling her Companion Shen.
(Song Zhi: Is everyone ready? Let's go.)
What good did we get when Shen was in favor?
Now that she's a Companion,
not only everyone treads upon her,
but also kicks on us.
What kind of a world is this?
That's enough. Keep it to yourself.
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Aiyi, you are still here, My Lady.
You should go.
The wars in the northwest are tense.
His Majesty spent all his time at court
and the Governance Hall for the past few days
reading the memorandums or meeting the ministers.
I'm afraid His Majesty doesn't really have time for you.
Thank you, Mr Su. I'd prefer to keep waiting.
My Lady, I understand that you are anxious about Companion Shen.
But you must care for your health.
My Lady, please.
Thank you very much, sir.
What a scorching day!
It was so much cooler inside.
Lady Sourire.
Why are you standing in the sun?
Is it because you're trying get rid of the mold on you?
[mold (霉) also means "bad luck"]
Peace and grace to Your Highness.
Of course, I'm able to have peace and grace
when the rats are caught in the palace.
You may rise.
Isn't His Majesty busy with the state affairs?
He is.
His Majesty is concerned about
my brother amid the wars in the northwest.
I just received a letter from my brother
and had to share every detail with His Majesty.
I thank Your Highness for the information.
I wonder if His Majesty is available at the moment.
His Majesty is with Lady Cao and Princess Wenyi.
Lady Sourire, do you intend to go inside
and intercede for Shen Meizhuang?
His Majesty has been irked for several days.
Now he is finally able to enjoy some time off with his daughter.
Your intrusion will remind His Majesty of Shen's
feigned pregnancy whether you mention it or not.
Do you think His Majesty will be more upset?
I believe Meizhuang would never do such a thing.
Hmph!
Will His Majesty trust you or the facts?
Shen Meizhuang must be really blessed
by her ancestors to not have been executed.
Her foolishness over the imperial heirs
will lead to her lonely death in the palace.
Aiya, the sun is blazing.
- Song Zhi, we'll go.
- Yes.
Mr Su, may I trouble you once more to
inform His Majesty of my request for audience?
Your Majesty, Lady Sourire is still waiting to see you.
Your Majesty, please let her in.
On such a hot day, she might get sun stroke
as she is so worried about Companion Shen.
Companion Shen will also be distressed if Lady Sourire is unwell.
Companion Shen wouldn't be able to devote herself to the time-out.
I like the lullaby you sang.
You should sing it again to Wenyi.
Certainly.
(singing) Back and forth, my dear love,
it's time for forty winks.
His Majesty is not willing to listen to you, My Lady,
or think about Companion Shen.
My Lady, please go.
Thank you, sir.
My Lady, shall we go see the Empress?
Meizhuang, think positively.
You have to care for your health until the day you are exonerated.
Thank you for making the trip to take care of me.
You reside in my palace, but I wasn't able to take care
of you for my inexperience in pregnancy.
I'm the only one that is permitted to visit you once in a while.
Lady Sourire is really concerned about you,
but she couldn't get past all the guards outside.
Please tell her to ensure the protection of herself.
Don't offend His Majesty by speaking for me.
Meizhuang, nothing I say to her can
matter as much as your caring for yourself.
Lady Sourire will have a difficult time if you are unwell.
All right, I'll eat.
My Lady, you should stop peeling the lotus pod.
It took a lot of care to grow your scallion-white fingernails.
I can't help feeling apprehensive at this point.
Concubine Estime does not have a heart of stone.
She will take care of her.
Meizhuang suddenly fell out of favor from a prime position.
Even though His Majesty is lenient with her,
no one in the palace is easy to deal with.
How Meizhuang must be trampled on!
Meizhuang is not a person to swallow her pride.
What if she ...
My Lady.
How about we turn to Madam Orchid?
She was your etiquette teacher,
and now she serves His Majesty directly.
Give it to her privately.
Tell her I need her help to take care of Meizhuang.
Yes.
And give her a tube of Persian Brow Ink from my dresser.
Say it'll be nice on her eyebrows at work.
- My Lady ...
- Just go.
The food is cold.
Shall I ask them to change for something warm?
It's all right. The Household Department
only has one meal sent to me daily.
Your chamber is heavily guarded.
I'm not even able to bring anything in here.
Hold on.
Did you say your meals were sent
by order of the Household Department?
Yes.
You can never be too careful to protect yourself.
[Silver turns dark in contact with sulfur.]
It's poisoned!
What's going on?
Ah, nothing. The bowl slipped out of Companion Shen's hand.
You may leave.
My Lady.
My Lady, it was informed by the Attendant Service
that His Majesty will visit Consort Fleur tonight.
The more His Majesty goes to her,
the more he is averse to Meizhuang.
I'm afraid he is also suspicious of me now.
That's why he's been avoiding me all this time.
It might be true that His Majesty is just busy with the state affairs.
My Lady, you share the pillow with His Majesty,
and he is particularly intimate to you.
If His Majesty had confidence in me, he would
see me immediately after the disposition of Meizhuang.
He wouldn't ignore me or turn me away.
They share their pillows with His Majesty as well.
I am not any different from them.
Estime,
His Majesty is afraid that I might
tarnish the repute of the imperial family.
He needed my life to be ended.
No, it's not like that, Meizhuang.
His Majesty is not a heartless person
and he would care for the power of your family.
If you died in my palace, they would say you
had committed suicide out of guilty conscience.
And I would also be held accountable.
There is only one person who would
do such harm to you and me.
You mean ... Consort Fleur!
I could never underestimate her ruthlessness.
How defensive she was against me with all her hate!
How she spent every bit of her time on my tortures.
Estime, you must tell His Majesty!
But I'm afraid the words from my
humble being carry no weight to His Majesty.
If they have the intention to kill you,
they will make it appear to be a guilty suicide.
Telling His Majesty is to "beat the grass and startle the snakes".
But ... how about my meals?
Not only the meals, you must keep an eye out
for tampering in everything from now.
I will request the Empress to allow
your meals to be made in my palace.
That would save the trouble with the Imperial Kitchen.
Thank you for saving my life.
Please don't tell Huan'er about this
in case she loses control of her mind.
I'll do anything to protect you as it is to protect myself.
I understand what to do with Lady Sourire.
Your Majesty, the tea might still be hot.
You inked your eyebrows as "distant mountains".
[In ink painting, you only see the mountain ridges.]
Yes, I remember it from drawing eyebrows for Empress Première.
Oh.
Peace to Lady Sourire.
My Lady, His Majesty will be here tonight.
Please get ready.
- Thank you, sir.
- Allow me to take my leave.
His Majesty is finally going to see you, My Lady.
Will you find a chance to speak for Meizhuang?
I don't dare to when I finally have the chance to.
I'll have to wait for a chance
after His Majesty feels better about it.
It is reasonable to protect yourself under such circumstances.
I'll take every chance I can to help her.
I lost my head previously.
Did you see anyone who was not hoping
that I would beg my way into trouble?
I cannot let that happen.
If only we could have evidence for Meizhuang's innocence.
I know she must have been framed.
But there's nothing I can do when we have no evidence.
Right, Vermilion, send Xiao-Yunzi to see
Wen Shichu at Duke Pei's residence.
He'll bring my notes to my parents and
Meizhuang's grandparents in Beijing.
They have to find Liu Ben
either dead or alive.
I don't believe he could vanish without a trace.
Yes, My Lady.
Huang Guiquan has been better at his job.
He dared to send such flowers to me.
What a snobbish rat!
How dare he jerk us around
when His Majesty has not been visiting!
I'll move it out of your sight, My Lady.
I can't even imagine Meizhuang's situation
when I am treated like this.
Put the pomegranate flowers to the most
conspicuous place in the yard before the dawn.
It will always remind me of today.
I'm afraid His Majesty won't visit
as he hasn't arrived by this time.
Would you go to sleep now, My Lady?
It's all right.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
I'm exhausted.
Would Your Majesty like some sweet soup?
It was cooled with ice earlier, and not very cold now.
It's better to not have cold food late at night.
I put jasmine flowers in the chamber
so that Your Majesty will sleep soundly tonight.
You don't have anything else to tell me?
The sun is blazing in the summer,
and the gold hairpins can be dazzling to the eyes.
However, those made of fishbone are hardly noticeable.
Si Lang, do you think I should use coral or black jade?
And that was your urgent problem?
It is important for a girl to dress nicely
for the man that makes her happy.
Certainly, of paramount importance.
In my view,
the red coral will look lovely against your fair skin.
Thanks, Si Lang.
You don't speak for Shen?
"We can tell the strength of the horse from the number
of miles, and the heart of a person over the pass of days."
We'll find a trace if there was any left.
So why did you keep asking to see me?
You didn't see me for days, Si Lang.
Why am I not allowed to go to see you?
They all believed you were involved
in Shen's case as her closest friend.
Why do you not say anything for yourself?
"A rumor spread three times is more dangerous than a tiger."
But Si Lang is a sagacious emperor,
and you know the person I am.
You wouldn't believe a one-sided story.
Si Lang, if you had any doubts in me, I wouldn't
be here talking with you heart-to-heart, would I?
Why do you trust that I have no doubts in you?
You are the one I share the pillow with.
If I don't trust you, who can I possibly trust or rely on?
You have made a decision about Meizhuang,
and I will not say anything about it.
And you already told me that I might have some troubles
with Consort Fleur after she regains her status.
I will not put you in a difficult position.
You've been very busy lately.
You should sleep now.
Your Majesty, I heard that Huang Guiquan did
something wrong and was sent to the Department of Penalty.
That's correct. He was too careless in his job.
This morning when His Majesty woke at Lady Sourire's
residence, he was greeted by an array of withered flowers.
His Majesty got angry and sent him away.
It was nothing important.
Let him come back in a few days.
Everything matters when it comes to serving the concubines.
While he may be careless about yardwork,
he might also get negligent in preparing the meals,
or even humiliatingly get in a concubine's face.
I understand he is a relative of yours,
that is why we need to be strict with him this time.
You have a kind heart and don't see the consequence of it.
But he might be considered abusing power under your influence.
That might not only hurt your reputation,
but also dismay His Majesty.
I was just thinking that it would be difficult to find a replacement
with equivalent experience in the Household Department.
I didn't mean anything like that.
That is why we must disassociate you from his
wrongdoings in honor of your good name.
Of course, as for his replacement, I have promoted the
deputy head, Jiang Zhongmin, to the department head.
Your Majesty makes decision at lightning speed.
Your Majesty was saying that His Majesty
saw the flowers in Lady Sourire's yard.
But the Attendance Services recorded that His Majesty
selected Consort Fleur for last night.
How did His Majesty end up with Lady Sourire?
It might well be an impulse of His Majesty.
Certainly.
Had Consort Fleur been able to keep
His Majesty from visiting Lady Sourire,
Huang Guiquan would not be in such bad luck.
[translators] Carsen and Maxwell
[to join mailing list] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[communication homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.